Thelner Barton Hoover (UCLA 1930) and Louise Eleanor Brown Hoover (UCLA 1930) photographic collection, 1921-1982. UARC.0647
UCLA Library Special Collections
Thelner Barton Hoover (UCLA 1930) and Louise Eleanor Brown Hoover (UCLA 1930) photographic collection
1921-1982
UCLA Library Special Collections
Hoover, Louise Eleanor Brown
Hoover, Thelner Barton
UARC.0647
122 Linear Feet [41 cartons (41 linear ft.) 26 shoe boxes (5.2 linear ft.) 65 film reels (75.8 linear ft.)]
Record Series 647 contains the photographic and manuscript materials of Thelner Barton Hoover (UCLA 1930) and Louise Eleanor Brown Hoover (UCLA 1930).
Conditions Governing Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance through our electronic paging system using the "Request items" button.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Existence and Location of Copies note for the link to the digitized materials.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9945140773606533
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
The collection was a gift from the Louise Hoover Trust, donated April 4, 1991. Additional items were donated by Keith Brown in December 1996.
Biographical Note
Thelner Barton Hoover, photographer, and his wife, Louise Brown Hoover, both UCLA Class of 1930, served UCLA in various capacities for over 50 years. Thelner B. Hoover began his career in 1921 as a student photographer for his Rockford Illinois high school yearbook. When his family moved to California, he attended Pasadena Junior College, and was the official student photographer for that campus from 1925 until graduating in 1927. T.B. Hoover attended the University of California, Los Angeles from 1927 until he graduated in 1930. He was a member of the Sigma Alpha Epsilon (SAE) fraternity. He was the official student photographer for "The Southern Campus" yearbook, the Daily Bruin (student newspaper) and the Athletic News Bureau. As a student, he financed and co-produced with Bud Graybill, a 35mm film entitled "The Bruin Review," which featured the move from the Vermont Campus to Westwood. This film was a part of the student Charter Day event in March 1930. Thelner made films of UCLA football games before Stan Troutman took over. He began a series of aerial photographs of the campus and the surrounding community in 1929 and continued this series after graduation. Thelner continued to document UCLA after his graduation. Some of his photographs are included in "UCLA on the Move" by John B. Jackson and Andrew Hamilton, and in "California of the Southland" published in 1937.
In 1938, Thelner became the manager of the Westwood Village Studio, a photography studio specializing in portraits. He was the official photographer for the Southern California Tennis Association from 1929 until 1942. He photographed many events and VIPs at many of the Westside country clubs and hotels, particularly the Beverly Wilshire. He photographed the Las Floristas Headress Ball, national conventions of the Delta Zeta, Pi Beta Pi and Alpha Chi Delta sororities. His photographs were published in many national magazines including color covers of "Sunset Magazine" and the "Los Angeles Times Home Magazine." Thelner Hoover was a photography instructor for UCLA Extension Division for 20 years. He opened the Department of Journalism at Pasadena City College and taught Pictorial Journalism for four years. Thelner also belonged to the Westwood Village Lion's Club for 39 years and served as its president. And he was a member of the Blue Key Men's Honorary. He was active in the UCLA Alumni Association for many years and served as the Alumni Travel Chairman and official photographer. He was also co-chair with his wife, Louise, for the 1975 reunion of the Class of 1930.
Louise E. Brown (Hoover) was a member of the Delta Zeta Sorority, Alpha Chi Chapter, UCLA. She was active in the University Dramatic Society and worked for the Athletic News Bureau as a UCLA student. After graduation, she worked as a radio actress. Louise Brown and Thelner Hoover were married in August 1930. Louise Hoover began an active association with many different UCLA service clubs and organizations after she graduated. L. Hoover was a member of the Alumni Council from 1945 until 1947. She was a life member of the Alumni Assocation, serving as Vice President from 1949 until 1951. She served on many Alumni Association committees including the Scholarship, Charter Day and Homecoming committees. Louise was an active member of the Gold Shield for 33 years and served both on the board and as Vice President. She was a charter member of the Westwood Women's Bruin Club, and was a long-time member of the Affiliates, serving on the Board and as Vice President. Louise Hoover served as the Class of 1930 secretary for many years and helped organize various reunions of that class.
Scope and Content
Record Series 647 (The Thelner and Louise Hoover collection, spanning the years 1921-1982) consists primarily of Thelner Hoover's photographs and negatives. The collection contains black and white photographs, color photographs, negatives, color slides, 16mm films, and a few daguerrotypes, tintypes, ambrotypes, glass lantern slides, glass negatives and two autochromes. The collection also includes personal papers and manuscripts relating to Thelner and Louise's personal life, travels, their involvement with UCLA, and Thelner's professional work.
The majority of the photographs are Hoover's professional portraits of individuals and groups, and of social, business, and sporting events in the West Los Angeles area. There are photographs of brides and weddings; events at the Beverly Wilshire Hotel; celebrities and political figures, including Ronald and Nancy Reagan; sporting events, including those of the Southern California Tennis Association; many social events and conferences of various sororities, including Delta Zeta, Alpha Chi Delta, Alpha Delta Pi; fraternities, such as Sigma Alpha Epsilon; various women's groups; the Las Floristas Headress Balls; and examples of his product and architecture photography. The majority of these photographs are not specifically identified.
The collection also contains Hoover's personal family photographs. The earliest photographs, estimated to be in the late 1800's, are of the generation preceding him and his wife. It may be that the daguerrotypes, ambrotypes, and tintypes are Hoover or Brown family members or it may be his collection of early photographic techniques, as these portraits are not identified. There are early portraits of Thelner and Louise, their wedding portraits, and those of their two daughters, Janeen and Lisa. The collection contains many photographs of social occasions and celebrations of holidays with their friends and family.
The Hoovers traveled a great deal and documented their trips well. Thelner's early artistic photography work focused on landscape. His later travel photographs reflect some of this early interest in landscape, but expanded to include the documentation of the place, its architecture and life. In addition to some of the fine art photography, the collection also includes many snapshot travel photographs. The collection documents Sequoia and Yosemite from the late 1920s and early 1930s; Idyllwild in the late 1930s; Lake Tahoe in 1930 (taken during their honeymoon); Taxco, Mexico in the late 1930s; Lake Tagish (Yukon) in 1938; and the Canadian Rockies in the early 1940s. There are photographs of Alaska, Hawaii, Mexico, Canada, France, Holland, Denmark, Yugoslavia, Australia, New Zealand, Bangkok, Tokyo, Bali, Hong Kong, Tahiti, and other locations.
The UCLA collection of photographs ranges from the State Normal School in 1925 through the Alumni Association Awards in 1982. Thelner documented the history of UCLA beginning with the Vermont Avenue Campus in 1927; the Westwood Campus groundbreaking ceremony in 1927; photographs of book illustrations of the Italian buildings which inspired the architecture of Royce Hall and the Powell Library buildings; the construction of Royce Hall, the Powell Library, and Kinsey Hall (the Physics building); the UCLA Band in 1928; models of the earliest buildings: Chemistry, Haines, Moore, and others; and the moving days to the Westwood campus. There are only portions or strips of his film, "The Bruin Review" identified in the collection. A highlights of the collection includes the construction of Royce Hall and the Powell Library building. There are 1929 glass negatives which depict the Powell Library and UCLA's 1st registration; while the two autochromes show Haines Hall and Louise Brown.
Thelner began a series of aerial photographs of the UCLA campus and surrounding area of Westwood in 1929. He photographed the campus from the air again in January and April 1930, in 1936 (from the Goodyear Blimp), 1938, and 1952. The collection contains photographs of the dedication of his aerial mural which was hung in the UCLA Ackerman Student Union Westwood Room in 1962 and was later moved to the University Religious Conference Building.
Thelner recorded the dedication of UCLA on March 26, 1930. The collection contains over sixty negatives and prints of this ceremony, with portraits of President Campbell, Sproul, Moore, Barrett, Hedricks, Dickson, Dodd, John Dewey, Case, Gimble, and others. It also contains photographs of the Mira Hershey Hall dedication, commencement, the Bookstore and Coop, football practice, the first snowfall on campus in 1932, and the Clark Library fourth Annual celebration in 1948. Other events in the collection include John Wooden's last game, the Class of 1930's 30th and 40th reunion, and the 1982 Alumni Association Awards. There are various sports photographs of basketball, track, and tennis. And there are photographs of the Sigma Alpha Epsilon (SAE) fraternity presenting UCLA Football coach Tommy Prothero with the Distinguished Alumnus Award. Thelner photographed many dignitaries and UCLA important people such as Dwight Eisenhower, Charles Young, Ralph Freud, Kenneth McGowan, Arthur Ashe, Robert B. Campbell, Edwin Pauley, Franklin Murphy, and many others as yet unidentified. He photographed Ralph Bunche, John Wooden, and Lew Alcindor (Kareem Abdul-Jabbar). However, these negatives or prints have yet to be located within the collection.
In addition to the photographs, there are 65 cannisters of 16mm films, 12 reels of 16mm and 6 reels of sound recording tape, and 5 reels of 16mm film identified as UCLA. These films have not yet been assessed for content.
Included in the personal papers and manuscript materials of the collection are publicity newspaper articles; UCLA Alumni Association travel records and Alumni magazines; information about Gold Shield, the Affiliates, Westwood Women's Bruin Club, and the UCLA University Club; information about Delta Zeta and Sigma Alpha Epsilon; records of his photography business; and miscellaneous memorabilia. In addition, there are yearbooks from UCLA's "The Southern Campus," years 1941 and 1942; Pasadena High School, years 1918, 1925, and 1928; Pasadena Junior College, 1928; and Pasadena City College, years 1948 and 1950. The collection contains some objects, such as two 4 x 5 wooden negative holders, a slide attache case, and two boxes of mats imprinted with his business name.
This is an inactive record series; no additional University records are expected to be added.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digitized materials are available electronically at https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/3vb00000zz-89112.
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Westwood Women's Bruin Club. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Charter Banquet. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Miscellaneous, includes class of 1929 yearbook photocopy. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Miscellaneous, includes Royce Hall cards. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Gold Shield. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Alumni Association. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Alumni Association Travel. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Alumni Magazine. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. The Affiliates. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. University Club. (Box 1)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Louise Hoover and Delta Zeta. (Box 2)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Louise Hoover and Alumni Association. (Box 2)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Thelner Hoover and Sigma Alpha Epsilon. (Box 2)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Thelner Hoover, photographer. (Box 2)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Alumni Association Tours, Louise Hoover's writing. (Box 2)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Newspaper clippings. (Box 3)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Travel, Hawaii., 1951. (Box 4)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Travel, Hoover family vacation., 1951. (Box 4)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Travel, Guatemala, Yucatan and Mexico., 1960. (Box 4)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Travel, Europe., 1952. (Box 5)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Miscellaneous. (Box 5)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Miscellaneous. (Box 6)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Miscellaneous. (Box 7)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Miscellaneous. (Box 8)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Yearbooks, Rockford Illinois High School., 1925. (Box 9)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Yearbooks, Pasadena High School., 1918; 1925; 1927. (Box 9)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Yearbooks, Pasadena Jr College. 2 copies. (Box 10)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Yearbooks, Pasadena High School. (Box 10)
- UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Yearbooks, Southern Campus. (Box 11)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Yearbooks, Pasadena City College., 1948-1950. (Box 12)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. ARCS Foundation Los Angeles Chapter 8th Annual Ball., 1974 Jun 22. (Box 12)
- Non-UCLA. Manuscripts and personal papers. Las Floristas. (Box 13)
- Non-UCLA. Work order index cards with names and dates. (Box 14)
- Non-UCLA. Empty negative and print sleeves with dates and event. (Box 15)
- Non-UCLA. Mats with Thelner Hoover's studio name embossed. (Box 16)
- Non-UCLA. Mats with Thelner Hoover's studio name embossed. (Box 17)
- Non-UCLA. Negative holders, 2 wood 4x5. (Box 18)
- Non-UCLA. Slide case and 3 signed mats. (Box 19)
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Italian buildings illustrations, models for Powell Library & Royce Hall., 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Church of San Sepokro, design for Powell Library or Royce Hall; St Stefano in Bologna, design for Powell Library or Royce Hall, illustration; St Stefano interior in Bologna, design for Powell Library or Royce Hall, illustration; St Ambrose atrium in Milan, design for Powell Library or Royce Hall; Church of San Zenove porch in Verona, design for Powell Library or Royce Hall; St Seplocro in St Stefano in Bologna, design for Powell Library or Royce Hall; Basiclica di S. Ambrogia, design for Powell Library or Royce Hall; La Chiesa S. Ambrogio in Milan, design for Powell Library or Royce Hall. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Campus construction, Royce Hall, Powell Library & Kinsey Hall (Physics)., ca. 1927-1929.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 2)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Campus construction; Campus bridge; Kinsey Hall (Physics building) construction; Royce Hall construction.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Royce Hall construction., ca. 1927-1929.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Royce Hall construction, auditorium; Royce Hall construction; Royce Hall; Royce Hall, exterior; Royce Hall construction, interior details. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Powell Library construction., ca. 1927-1929.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  General note
  Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Kinsey Hall (Physics Building)., ca. 1929-1932.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 5)
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Campus construction, Royce Hall & Powell Library., ca. 1927-1929.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Campus construction; Powell Library, interior; Powell Library; Royce Hall; Models of campus buildings; Campus bridge. Original negatives maybe found in box 28.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. State Normal School., ca. 1927-1930.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 7)
  Original negatives maybe found in box 28.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Band with John Phillip Souza., 1928 Oct 19.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 8)
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Vermont Avenue campus., 1928-1929.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 9)
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Portraits, Thelner Hoover & Louise Brown (Hoover) & others., ca. 1928-1930.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives (Box 20, Folder 10)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Thelner Hoover; Louise Brown (Hoover); Thelner Hoover & Durward ""Bud"" Graybill; Unidentified. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Models of campus buildings, Chemistry, Haines Hall, Kinsey Hall., ca. 1929.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 11)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Model of Chemistry Building; Model of Moore Hall or Social Science Building; Model of Haines Hall; Model of Kinsey Hall. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. High Jinx., 1929 Fall.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 12)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: High Jinx, campus event. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. All that Glitters Play, Delta Gala., 2.25x3 and 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives (Box 20, Folder 13)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: All that Glitters play for Delta Gala. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Negatives & prints. Groundbreaking for the Westwood campus., 1927 Sep 09.; 4x5 and 5x7 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 20, Folder 14)
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Southern campus, moving in days., 1929 May 11.; 4x5 and 5x7 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Royce Hall; Powell Library; Powell Library, temporary bookstore (lower right). Original negatives maybe found in boxes 27 and 28.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Aerial views & flight crew., 1929 Apr 11.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Graf zepplin from Ford TriMotor plane, for aerial photography; Aerial crew; Aerial crew, pilot Col Browlay, JB Avery; Aerial view, Beverly Hills; Aerial view, Santa Monica bay; Aerial view, 20th Century Fox Studio; Aerial view, campus; Aerial crew, Thelner Hoover, editor JB Avery; Aerial view, Westwood Hills; Aerial view, West Los Angeles. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Campus dedication., 1930 Mar 26.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Dedication, President William W. Campbell & Dr. Robert G. Sproul; Dedication, President William Wallace Campbell; Dedication, President William W. Campbell & Dr. Ernest C. Moore; Dedication, unidentified; Dedication, President William W. Campbell, Dr. Moore & Dr. Robert G. Sproul; Dedication, President William W. Campbell, Rieber & Dr. Ernest C. Moore; Dedication, Joe Crail & Dr. Barrett; Dedication, John Dewey; Dedication, Dr. Skylard, Franz; Dedication, Ed Dickson & Wes Cazel; Dedication, Jake Gimbel, Underhill & Chas Dodd; Dedication, Dr. Robert G. Sproul & others; Dedication, Jake Gimbel; Dedication, Dr. Hedricks & Mrs. Hedricks; Dedication, Dr. Robert G. Sproul; Dedication, Dr. Robert G. Sproul & others; Dedication, Davies; Dedication, unidentified; Dedication, President William W. Campbell & Mrs. Campbell; Dedication, Dr. Bjork; Dedication, Kenny Piper, Dr. Ernest Carroll Moore, Robert Keith, Lowell Stanley. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Southern Campus, Mechanical Arts Building., ca. 1930-1934.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Mechanical Arts Building; Campus; Powell Library. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Campus & Westwood., 1930 Jan 10.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 21, Folder 5)
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Aerial views., 1930 Jan 21.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Aerial view, campus. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Aerial views., 1930 Apr 28.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Aerial view, campus; Aerial view, Powell Library; Aerial view, Royce Hall; Aerial view, Royce Hall, campus, bridge. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. UC President Campbell., 1930 Feb 11.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: UC President William W. Campbell; UC President William W. Campbell & Dr. Walter Morris Hart. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Campus registration., 1930 Feb.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives (Box 21, Folder 9)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Registration; UC President Campbell. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Campus commencement., 1930.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives (Box 21, Folder 10)
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Commencement, Greek Theater., ca. 1930-1941.; 2.25x3 and 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  Original negatives maybe found in boxes 27 and 29.
- UCLA. UCLA Movie, Bruin Review, excerpts for the yearbook., 1930.; 35mm black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 22, Folder 2)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Bruin Review, film sections. Original negatives maybe found in box 27.
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Kerkhoff Hall dedication., 1931 Jan 20.; 4x5 black & white nitrate negatives. (Box 22, Folder 3)
- UCLA. BW Photographs, copy negatives & contact prints. Bookstore & Coop., 1931 Sep.; 4x5 black & white safety negatives. (Box 22, Folder 4)
  This folder includes negatives of the following: Campus bookstore. Original negatives maybe found in box 29.